Guide to the Communist Workers Party Records TAM.231
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Workers Party Records
1976-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Workers Party (U.S.)
Janken, Kenneth
TAM.231
0.67 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 half manuscript box
The Communist Workers Party (CWP, 1979-1985) was a U.S. Maoist oganization that originated in 1973 as the Asian Study Group (renamed the Workers' Viewpoint Organization in 1976); it was established by Jerry Tung. After the "Greensboro (North Carolina) Massacre" of 1979, in which five people were killed during an anti-Ku Klux Klan rally by the American Nazi Party, the CWP relinquished its Leninist structure and moved towards a social democratic framework. In 1985, the CWP became the New Democratic Movement (NDM), which lasted only a few years. The Communist Workers Party Records (1976-1987) contains materials collected and created by the CWP, and later, the NDM. These materials include bulletins, position papers, memos, speeches, publications, and the Third National Party Congress bulletins.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Provenance unknown, most likely donated by Kenneth Janken in 1989. The accession number associated with this collection is 1989.017.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Historical Note
The Communist Workers Party (CWP, 1979-1985) was a U.S. Maoist oganization that originated in 1973 as the Asian Study Group (renamed the Workers' Viewpoint Organization in 1976). It was established by Jerry Tung, a former member of the Progressive Labor Party. The CWP is best known for the "Greensboro (North Carolina) Massacre" of 1979, in which the American Nazi Party attacked an anti-Ku Klux Klan rally held by the CWP, shooting and killing five people, including two CWP members. The CWP supported the "Gang of Four," the prominent followers of Mao ZeDong imprisoned in China after Mao's death, but after the massacre, the group relinquished its Leninist structure and moved towards a social democratic framework. In 1985, the CWP became the New Democratic Movement (NDM), which lasted only a few years. The most important remnant of the CWP/NDM can be found in the Greensboro Justice Fund which promotes groups struggling for social justice.
Scope and Contents
The Communist Workers Party Records (1976-1987) contains materials collected and created by the CWP, and later, the NDM. These materials include bulletins, position papers, memos, speeches, publications (including the newsletters and journals The National Bulletin/New Democratic Bulletin and The Expert Red: Handbook for American Revolutionaries, and individual publications such as The Current Revolutionary Situation: Our Tasks), and the Third National Party Congress bulletins. Although this collection does not contain materials about the Greensboro Massacre itself, the aftermath and response by the CWP are reflected in speeches, position papers, and proposals. Additionally, publications such as The Post Industrial Society (circa 1986), a position paper of the NDM, and meeting materials from the board, illustrate the evolution of the organization from the CWP to the NDM.
Maoist parties |z United States.; Greensboro (N.C.); Maoism -- United States.; Massacres |z North Carolina |z Greensboro |x History |y 20th century.; Tung, Jerry; Communist Workers Party (U.S.); Janken, Kenneth
- Workers Viewpoint Organization -- Eternal Glory to Chairman Mao, Greatest Marxist of the Contemporary Era, September-October 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Speeches, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes and Notebooks, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Program of the CWP, USA" -- Draft, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Departmental Bulletins, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Secretariat and Task Force Meeting Notes, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Working Papers, Proposals, and Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- National Bulletin/New Democratic Bulletin, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Internal Memos and Correspondence, 1980-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- CWP/NDM Publications -- Position Papers, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- The Expert Red: Handbook for American Revolutionaries, December 1984-March 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Third National Party Congress -- Bulletins and Agenda, March-May 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- NDM Board Meeting Materials and Memos, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- NDM -- New York State Bulletin -- Vol. 1, #2, February 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Asian Americans for Equality, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Plotnick, Jonathan and Justin Schwartz -- "The United States and the World", circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)